

#### PHD CANDIDATE IN COMPUTER SCIENCE · RESEARCHER (SOFTWARE ENGINEERING-HCI

Fairfax, Virginia, USA

💌 smhasanmansur@qmail.com | 🏕 smhasanmansur.netlify.app | 🖸 hasanmansur | 🛅 smhasanmansur | 📂 S M Hasan Mansur

## Summary\_

Research focus: "Automated Software Engineering via Multimodal Machine Learning". Research Interests: Software Engineering, HCI, Machine Learning, Generative AI and Large Language Model (LLM). . Publication track record in top-tier SWE venues. 5+ years of professional experience in developing scalable, distributed, and enterprise-grade products. Open to relocation and no sponsorship required.

# **Professional Experience**

#### **George Mason University**

Virginia, USA

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

May 2021 - Aug 2024

- · Areas of Contribution: Ethical Software Design, Software Evolution, Software Accessibility and Software Documentation.
- Currently leading a research project aimed toward developing a multimodal model (vision-code-comment) for code summarization.
- Designed and developed AidUI, an automated approach to detect and localize deceptive design patterns on UIs.
- · Co-contributor of MotorEase, an approach to detect motor-impairment accessibility violations in app UIs.
- · Co-contributor of GUIEvo, an approach to update UI code by detecting changes between existing and proposed designs.
- Collaborated in developing datasets to serve as benchmarks for Bug Reporting and Bug Localization.

#### **George Mason University**

Virginia, USA

**GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT** 

Aug 2024 - Current | Aug 2018 - May 2021

• Mentored students, graded assignments, and proctored exams. Courses: Python Programming, Database, Computer Vision, Formal Methods.

Ice9 Ltd. Dhaka, Bangladesh

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Apr 2017 - Jul 2018

- Member of the core engineering team responsible for the development and maintenance of **SMASHBOARD.CO**, a social CRM product.
- · Collaborated with the Technical Lead on strategic planning and decision-making for architecture design, development, testing and deployment.
- · Lead the development and integration of social media query management and analytics module for INSTAGRAM.
- · Optimized database and implemented master-replica architecture to resolve the sync delay of real time social queries.
- Collaborated in implementing the migration of the core product from Rackspace to AWS.

Synchronous ICT Dhaka, Bangladesh

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Feb 2015 - Apr 2017

- · Lead the team to develop user management, search and notification platforms of project COMX, an in-house application framework.
- Assessed the capacity to deliver, formed sprints and released duration based development milestones.

**Dcastalia**Dhaka, Bangladesh

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Aug 2013 - Jan 2015

- Developed and published HE BUSINESS MANAGER, a native Android app for inventory management of healthcare products.
- · Collaborated with the backend team on requirements analysis, architecture design, development, testing and deployment.

#### Mercedes-Benz Group AG (former Daimler AG)

Ulm, Germany

STUDENT INTERN

Oct 2012 - Jul 2013

Developed a KVP (key-value pair) parser to convert the unstructured stream of environment perception data into a canonical form.

Grameenphone Ltd.

Dhaka, Bangladesh

System Engineer

Jul 2007 - Feb 2011

• Member of the transmission network configuration and optimization team to serve over 20 million mobile users.

# **Publications**

- Arun Krishnavajjala, S M Hasan Mansur, Justin Jose, Kevin Moran, "MotorEase: Automated Detection of Motor Impairment Accessibility Issues in Mobile App Uls", ICSE'24
- Junayed Mahmud, Nadeeshan De Silva, Safwat Ali Khan, Seyed Hooman Mostafavi, **S M Hasan Mansur**, Oscar Chaparro, Andrian (Andi) Marcus, Kevin Moran, "On Using GUI Interaction Data to Improve Text Retrieval-based Bug Localization", ICSE'24
- Sabiha Salma, S M Hasan Mansur, Kevin Moran, Yule Zhang, "GUIEvo: Automated Evolution of Mobile Application GUIs from Mockups", MSR'24
- S M Hasan Mansur, Kevin Moran, "Toward Automated Tools to Support Ethical GUI Design", ICSE'23: Companion Proceedings
- S M Hasan Mansur, Sabiha Salma, Damilola Awofisayo, Kevin Moran, "AidUl: Toward Automated Recognition of Dark Patterns in User Interfaces",
- Tyler Wendland, Jingyang Sun, Junayed Mahmud, S M Hasan Mansur, Steven Huang, Kevin Moran, Julia Rubin, Mattia Fazzini, "AndroR2: A
  Dataset of Manually-Reproduced Bug Reports for Android apps", MSR'21

### **Tech Skills**

**Programming** Python, Javascript, Java, C

**Databases** MySQL, MongoDB, Redis, Elasticsearch, SQLite **Libraries** OpenCV, NumPy, Matplotlib, Pandas, Socket.IO

ML/DL/NLP Transformer, LLM finetuning, PyTorch, Hugging Face, scikit-learn, spaCy

Backend/Cloud/DevOps Node.js, Express.js, REST API, AWS, Docker, Git

### Selected Research

#### **Multimodal Code Summarization**

Ongoing

PRINCIPAL CONTRIBUTOR | SAGE LAB, UCF

- Goal: To investigate how visual information from UI impacts in automated code summarization.
- · Identified the research gap after conducting literature review of related works. Formulated the design of approach to address the gap.
- Developed the data extraction pipeline to collect and map multi-modal data (code, comment, UI) from open-source app repositories.
- Currently leading the team to conduct data exploratory analysis and labeling of the dataset.
- Currently developing a model that aims toward learning from multi-modal data for code summarization.

AidUI Published, ICSE'23

PRINCIPAL CONTRIBUTOR | SAGE LAB, UCF

paper link, project repo

- AidUI is an automated approach to detect and localize deceptive design patterns on UIs.
- Developed a unified taxonomy and a set of heuristic rules to detect visual-textual cues that signify the presence of deceptive UI design patterns.
- Automated the data pipeline to extract UIs from publicly available app usage videos and screenshots by prior studies.
- · Designed and developed an approach that leverages computer vision and NLP techniques to detect different deceptive patterns on UI.
- Implemented an automated evaluation pipeline. Dockerized and published research artifacts in a public repository.

MotorEase Published, ICSE'24

CO-CONTRIBUTOR | SAGE LAB, UCF

paper link, project repo

- MotorEase is an approach to detect motor-impairment accessibility violations in app UIs.
- Developed the initial prototype of the "Semantic Text Matching" component of the automated approach.
- Collaborated with the lead contributor on labeling and curation of the dataset.

# Education \_\_\_\_\_

2018-25	George Mason University, PhD candidate in Computer Science	Virginia, USA
2023	George Mason University, MS in Computer Science	Virginia, USA
2007	Shah Jalal University of Science & Technology, BS in Computer Science	Bangladesh

### Honors & Awards \_\_\_\_\_

2023	NSF Travel Award, ICSE'23	Australia
2022	Best Poster Presentation Award, GMU CS Research Symposium	Virginia, USA
2019	Summer Research Initiation Award, GMU CS Dept.	Virginia, USA

# **Sel**ected Open Source Projects \_

2020	Ontorjal, Implementation of DNS client & Distance Vector Routing protocol.	project repo
2020	<b>Drishtipat</b> , Implementation of different concepts/topics of Computer Vision.	project repo
2017	<b>Tasky</b> , A backend boilerplate featuring Role Based Access Control, Searching, Token Authentication, TDD.	project repo

# **Professional Services**

2024	Junior PC Member, MSR'24
2022	Co-Reviewer, MSR'22
2021-23	External Reviewer, ICSE'21, ICSE'23, SANER'22, SANER'23, ASE'22, MSR'21, ICPC'21

# **Volunteering**\_

2022	<b>Co-Mentor</b> , Aspiring Scientists Summer Internship Program, GMU
2021-22	<b>Director-Web Services</b> , Bangladeshi Graduate Student Association, GMU
2002-07	Member, KIN, Humanitarian Organization, SUST, Bangladesh